Guide to the Abe Burrows papers, 1904-1993
The New York Public Library. Billy Rose Theatre Division.
Abe Burrows papers
1904-1993
*T-Mss 2000-006
21645
Burrows, Abe, 1910-1985
The New York Public Library. Billy Rose Theatre Division. New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, Dorothy and Lewis B. Cullman Center 40 Lincoln Center Plaza, New York, NY 10023-7498
50 lin. ft. 97 boxes, 29 volumes and 3 oversized folders
This collection of personal papers, correspondence, production files, radio scripts, autobiographical writings, interviews, speeches, articles, songs, clippings, photographs and visual materials provides a wealth of documentation on the personal and professional life of Pulitzer prize-winning playwright, lyricist, director, screenwriter, comedian and play doctor, Abe Burrows.
Abe Burrows, playwright, lyricist, director, screenwriter, comedian and play doctor was born Abram S. Burrows on December 18, 1910 in New York City to Louis and Julia Burrows. His father was in the paint and wallpaper business. He graduated from New Utrecht High School in Brooklyn and attended City College and New York University first in a pre-med program and then studying accounting. In 1931 he was hired by a brokerage firm on Wall Street where he worked for three years. He then worked in his father's paint business and as a traveling salesman for a maple syrup firm. During summers he was a popular entertainer in the Catskills and found he enjoyed making a living with his humor.
Burrows began selling radio sketches in 1938 and for four years was a writer for Ed Gardner's Duffy's Tavern, 1941-1945. He also wrote pieces for CBS Texaco Theater, The Joan Davis Show, and The Ford Program. In Hollywood he became a hit at exclusive parties with his satirical songs and recitations with titles such as The Girl with the Three Blue Eyes and I'm Walking down Memory Lane without a Single Thing to Remember. During the course of his career, he appeared on many radio and TV programs, recorded two albums of songs and published An Abe Burrows Songbook. In 1948 and 1949 he toured the country performing in nightclubs and also had his own radio shows: The Abe Burrows Show and Breakfast with Burrows.
Burrows' biggest hits, however, were in the world of musical theater. At CBS in Hollywood he had worked for Ernest Martin who later joined with Cy Feuer to produce Guys and Dolls. It was Martin who brought Burrows to work on the Broadway show. The Guys and Dolls that opened in November 1950 with book and lyrics by Burrows and music by Frank Loesser, was an award-winning production and major hit that ran for years and was revived in London, on Broadway and on school stages around the country. Burrows' other major hit, again with Frank Loesser, was How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying which won the Pulitzer Prize for drama in 1962.
From 1950 on Burrows' work was primarily for the Broadway stage as writer, director or both. In 1951 he doctored the musical Make a Wish, an adaption of Ferenc Molnar's The Good Fairy, and directed the revue, Two on the Aisle. In 1952 he was writer and director for Three Wishes for Jamie which he adapted with Charles O'Neal, in 1953 he wrote and directed Can-Can, and in 1954 he directed Reclining Figure. He adapted the screenplay of Ninotchka for the Cole Porter musical Silk Stockings and wrote the screenplay for Solid Gold Cadillac in 1955 and collaborated with Harry Kurnitz on Once More with Feeling in 1957 and with Richard and Marion Bissell on Say, Darling which he also directed in 1958. He was also writer and director for First Impressions, an adaptation of Pride and Prejudice and director of Golden Fleecing in 1959, for Cactus Flower, 1965, for Holly Golightly, 1966, a musical theater remake of the film Breakfast at Tiffany's which closed before its Broadway opening, and for Four on a Garden, 1971. His other directing credits include Happy Hunting, Golden Fleecing, What Makes Sammy Run?, Forty Carats, and No Hard Feelings. He was a director for Good News, 1974 and co-writer and director for Hellzapoppin', 1976, but left both shows before their openings. He also did some directing work on the show Forty-Second Street in 1981.
Burrows married his first wife Ruth in 1936. The couple had two children: James born in 1940 and Laurie in 1944, and were divorced in 1948. He married Carin Smith on October 2, 1950. Abe Burrows died on May 17, 1985 after a long illness.
This collection of personal papers, correspondence, production files, radio scripts, autobiographical writings, interviews, speeches, articles, songs, business files, clippings, photographs and other visual materials provides a wealth of documentation on Abe Burrows' personal and professional life. The early radio scripts of the comedian, the detailed files on each stage production especially Can-Can, How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying, and Cactus Flower, the large collection of opening night telegrams, and the extensive correspondence with family, friends and colleagues illuminate Burrows' personality and career. Includes long, informative and personal letters to his wife Carin when they were apart, working files for his Abe Burrows Songbook, 1955, articles, both published and unpublished, on show business and non-show business topics, sketches, notes and ideas for possible radio or television shows, movies or plays, various drafts of his autobiography, Honest Abe, 1980, caricatures and portrait photographs of Burrows as well as many shots of him with well known colleagues.
Series I: Personal Correspondence and Other Papers
Sub-series 1 - Correspondence between Abe and Carin Burrows
Sub-series 2 - Family Correspondence
Sub-series 3 - Personal Files
Sub-series 4 - Condolences
Series II: General Correspondence
Sub-series 1 - Letters
Sub-series 2 - Telegrams
Series III: Production Files
Sub-series 1 - By Title
Sub-series 2 - Not Produced
Sub-series 3 - Scripts sent to Burrows
Sub-series 4 - Professional Show Business Work
Series IV: Radio Scripts
Sub-series 1 - Unbound scripts
Sub-series 2 - Bound scripts
Series V: Songs / Abe Burrows Songbook
Series VI: Writings - Sketches, Articles, Speeches by
Series VII: Interviews and Articles about
Series VIII: Autobiography: Honest Abe
Series IX: Address books and calendars
Series X: Personal Business Files
Sub-series 1 - Legal
Sub-series 2 - Financial
Sub-series 3 - Medical
Series XI: Clippings
Series XII: Photographs and Other Visual Materials
Series XIII: Oversized Visual
The Abe Burrows Papers were donated to The Billy Rose Collection of the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts by James Burrows and Laurie Burrows Grad, the children of Abe Burrows, in 1999.
Audiovisual materials separated from archival collections are cataloged individually and can be found in the Library catalog. Search CATNYP, The New York Public Library catalog.
Tony Award for Guys and Dolls, 1950-1951
Tony Award for "Distinguished Achievement in Theatre," 1962
Crystal bar glass etched Can-Can
Souvenir cigarette case of First Impressions
Souvenir desk clock from Lauren Bacall to Abe Burrows for Cactus Flower
Cigarette lighter from Good News
Wooden plaque award to Burrows from Advertising Club of Baltimore, 1949
Wooden plaque, "Good Luck Abe Burrows" from KOCO TV, Oklahoma City
Plexiglass paperweight from Wililam Morris Agency
Pewter mug with initials AB
High school autograph book, 1924
Interlocking wooden puzzle, "Abe" (with broken "e")
Office door sign, "Mr. Burrows"
Eyeglasses (2 pairs)
Wooden stamp of Provincetown house, "Carin & Abe Burrows"
Wooden stamp of Provincetown house, "Merry Christmas & Happy New Year"
Stock ticker with glass cover
Ceramic ashtray, "Person to Person"
Six cocktail napkins embroidered "The Burrows"
Opening night note and silver dollar from Howard Teichmann
Leather notepad with "Abe Burrows" in his script stamped on
Keychains, lighters, money clips, etc. inscribed from Bing Crosby and others
Expired passports of Abe and Carin Burrows
Programme book with pencil tied on
Songs, A-Z, not part of production series
Records (78 rpm) from Abe Burrows Show
Records (78 rpm & 33 rpm) from other radio appearances
Cast albums
Show demos
Various reel to reel and cassette tapes
Various films and videos
Head shots (often with attached resumes) of actors hoping to audition for Abe Burrows
Souvenir program for Julie Harris in The Belle of Amherst
Miscellaneous standard programs for non-Burrows productions
Bissell, Richard, Say, Darling (Boston: Little, Brown & Co., 1957)
Burrows, Abe, The Abe Burrows Songbook(NY: Doubleday, 1955).
Capote, Truman, Breakfast at Tiffany's(NY: New American Library, Inc., 1958) (paperback)
The Greatest Revue Sketches, edited by Donald Oliver (NY: Avon books, 1982)
A libretto and a vocal book for Guys and Dolls published by Music Theatre International
Kurnitz, Harry, Reclining Figure(NY: Random House, 1955)
Lindsay, Howard, Happy Hunting(NY: Random House, 1957)
Mead, Shepherd, How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying ( NY: Simon and Schuster, 1952)
O'Neal, Charles, The Three Wishes of Jamie McRuin(NY: Julian Messner, Inc., 1949)
Schulberg, Budd, What Makes Sammy Run?(NY: Random House, 1965)
Wilde, Larry, How the Great Comedy Writers Create Laughter(Chicago, Nelson-Hall, 1976)
The Writer's World, edited by Elizabeth Janeway (NY: McGraw-Hill, 1969)
Plays in Samuel French pamphlets: Cactus Flower, First Impressions, Four on a Garden, Good News, and How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying.
Collection is open to the public. Library policy on photography and photocopying will apply. Advance notice may be required.
Photocopying prohibited.
Burrows, Abe, 1910-1985; Benoff, Mac; Braden, Bernard, 1916-; Burrows, Carin; Dolan, Robert Emmett, 1908-1972; Feuer, Cy; Galante, Pierre; Gardner, Ed, 1901-1963; Kahn, E. J. (Ely Jacques), 1916-1994; Kurnitz, Harry; Lewis, Arthur, 1916-1994; Loesser, Frank, 1910-1969; Mead, Shepherd; Porter, Cole, 1891-1964; Styne, Jule, 1905-1994; Vallée, Rudy, 1901-1986; Zolotow, Maurice, 1913-; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; Humorous songs; Musical theater -- New York (State) -- New York; Radio writers; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York; Theatrical producers and directors; Autobiographies; Caricatures; Contracts; Correspondence; Final drafts; First drafts; Photographs; Portrait photographs; Radio scripts; Scripts; telegrams; Comedians; Dramatists; Lyricists
- Series I: Personal Correspondence and Other Papers, 1904-1985; 588239; 4 boxes
  This series consists of personal correspondence between Abe Burrows and his wife Carin, correspondence with other family members, various materials documenting Abe Burrow's personal life such as holiday cards and gift lists, and condolences.
  - Sub-series 1 - Correspondence between Abe and Carin Burrows, 1946-1978 and n.d; 588240; 16 folders
    The sub-series is mainly long, handwritten letters from Abe to Carin when they were apart. The bulk is from 1948-1949 when he was on the road playing nightclubs and the summer of 1955 when he was in Hollywood writing a screenplay for Columbia Pictures Corporation. Also includes letters from Carin to Abe from the summer of 1955, poetry he wrote to her and notes and cards they exchanged. This is a rich file as the letters are long, informative and personal, shedding life on both Burrows' career and his marriage, and the handwriting is refreshingly clear.
    Chronological.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1948 Oct; 588241; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Letters, one telegram and two clippings from Abe Burrows performing in Chicago to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1948 Nov; 588242; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Letters from Abe Burrows performing in New York City to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1949 Feb; 588243; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Letters, poems and a few clippings from Abe Burrows performing in Minneapolis, Minnesota and St. Louis, Missouri to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1949 Mar; 588244; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Letters and a few clippings from Abe Burrows performing in St. Louis, Missouri, to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1949 Apr 15-May 20; 588245; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Letters and two telegrams from Abe Burrows performing in New York City to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1949 May 22-June 7; 588246; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Letters and a few clippings from Abe Burrows working in New York City to Carin Burrows at home in Hollywood.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1952; 588247; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Three letters and one telegram from Abe Burrows traveling in Beverly Hills, California and London and Paris to his wife, Carin Burrows, at home in New York City.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 June; 588248; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Letters from Abe Burrows working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood to his wife, Carin Burrows, at home in New York City.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 July 2-10; 588249; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 July 11-29; 588250; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Letters and a clipping from Abe Burrows working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood to his wife, Carin Burrows, at home in New York City.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 Aug 1-15; 588251 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Letters from Abe Burrows working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood to his wife, Carin Burrows, at home in New York City and in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 Aug 16-31; 588252; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Letters from Abe Burrows working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood to his wife, Carin Burrows, in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1955 Sept; 588253; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Letters and one telegram from Abe Burrows working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood to his wife, Carin Burrows, in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows, 1946-1978 and n.d; 588254; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Notes, cards and one telegram were sent from Abe Burrows to his wife Carin on birthdays, anniversaries, Valentine's Day, etc. One card is from Carin to Abe, and the 1946 material is addressed to Carin Kinzel before her marriage to Abe Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows., 588255; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Poetry [n.d.] by Abe Burrows to his wife, Carin.
    - Correspondence / Carin Burrows,., 1955 June-Aug; 588256; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Letters from Carin Burrows at home in New York City and in Provincetown, Massachusetts to her husband, Abe Burrows who was working for Columbia Pictures in Hollywood, California for the summer.
  - Sub-series 2 - Family Correspondence, 1945-1981; 588257; 29 folders
    This sub-series consists of correspondence with relatives from both Abe and Carin Burrows' families: parents, siblings, cousins, nieces and nephews. The most extensive correspondence is with Carin's parents, Jane and Karl K. Smith of Seattle, Washington. Many of these letters are by Abe.
    - Correspondence / James Burrows, 1958-1979 and n.d; 588258 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Correspondence of James and Roz Burrows with Abe Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Jonathan L. Burrows, 1957-1972 and n.d; 588259; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Correspondence between Jonathan Burrows and his uncle Abe Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Kenneth Burrows, 1955-1965 and n.d; 588260; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Correspondence between Kenny Burrows and his uncle Abe Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Louis Burrows,., 1946-1948; 588261; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, mostly letters by Louis Burrows to his son Abe Burrows, with some notes from his mother Julia as well. Includes a letter written by Abe Burrows to his father and returned to him because of his father's death and a copy of a letter Louis Burrows wrote to his other son Selig just before he died.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1948 Apr-May; 588262; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Condolence letters received on the death of his father Louis Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Selig S. Burrows,., 1951-1980; 588263; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Correspondence between Abe Burrows and his brother Selig.
    - Correspondence / Burrows family,., 1948-1981; 588264; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Correspondence between Abe Burrows and various cousins, aunts and uncles, etc.
    - Correspondence / Jeri Goss,., 1955-1961; 588265; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Correspondence between Jeri Goss (sister of Carin Burrows), her husband, E. Lyle Goss, and Abe and Carin Burrows.
      Goss, E. Lyle; Burrows, Carin; Correspondence
    - Correspondence / E. Lyle Goss,., 1962; 588266; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Correspondence between E. Lyle Goss, Carin Burrow's brother-in-law and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / E. Lyle Goss,., 1963-1969; 588267; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Correspondence between E. Lyle Goss, Carin Burrow's brother-in-law, and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / E. Lyle Goss,., 1971-1980; 588268; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Correspondence between E. Lyle Goss, Carin Burrow's brother-in-law, his wife Jeri and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Malinda Goss,., 1956-1965; 588269; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Correspondence between Malinda Goss, niece of Carin and Abe Burrows, with Abe and Carin Burrows. Also one letter by Malinda's sister Judi.
    - Correspondence / Salzberg family,., 1945-1962; 588270; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Correspondence between Abe Burrows and members of the Salzberg family, cousins on Abe Burrows' mother's side.
    - Correspondence / Salzman family,., 1970-1976; 588271; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Correspondence between Abe Burrows and members of the Salzman family, Burrows family cousins.
    - Correspondence / Jane Smith,., 1953-1954; 588272; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Correspondence between Jane Smith (mother of Carin Burrows), and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Jane Smith,., 1955-1956; 588273; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence / Jane Smith,., 1957; 588274; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence / Jane Smith,., 1958-1960; 588275; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence / John K. Smith,., 1956-1978; 588276; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Correspondence between Carin Burrows' brother, John K. Smith (a newspaper writer), his wife, Gerry, their young son, Kent K., and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1953-1961; 588277; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Correspondence between Karl K. Smith, father of Carin Burrows, and Abe and Carin Burrows.
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1962-1963; 588278; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1964-1965; 588279; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1966-1967; 588280; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1968-1969; 588281; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Correspondence between Karl K. Smith, father of Carin Burrows, and Abe and Carin Burrows. Also a copy of Smith's published book of poems, Homespun Rhymes, (NY: Carlton Press, 1968) inscribed to his "New York kids--Abe and Carin."
      Smith, Karl K; Homespun rhymes
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1970; 588282; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith,., 1971-1975; 588283; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence / Karl K. Smith, 1976 and n.d; 588284; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Smith-Bell family history / Karl K. Smith, n.d.; 588285; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Typescript, "The Smith-Bell Story as told by Karl K. Smith", Carin Burrow's father.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1953-1980; 588286; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Correspondence with unidentified relatives.
  - Sub-series 3 - Personal Files, 1904-1981 and n.d; 588287; 21 folders
    This sub-series of personal material pertaining to Abe Burrows includes his selective service papers, a small file of correspondence and a matrimonial agreement with his first wife, Ruth (related papers can be found in Series X. Subseries 1. Personal legal papers), files on travel to Europe 1952-1953, and California 1955, Christmas card and gift lists, incoming holiday cards, address lists for parties he gave, thank you notes received for charitable contributions and benefit appearances, correspondence with purveyors about wardrobe items, certificates and awards (except oversized ones: see Series XIII.), printed invitations and programs, letters from unidentified correspondents (no last names), miscellaneous ephemera and inquiries from libraries about the future of his papers. Also contains 3 handwritten pages of journal entries titled Silver Hill Inn and dated March-April, no year, which may be Burrows' last written words.
    - Selective service papers / Abe Burrows,., 1944-1945; 588288; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Orders to report for preinduction physical examination and notice of classification cards.
    - Divorce papers / Abe Burrows,., 1948-1962; 588289; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Abe Burrows' matrimonial agreement with his first wife, Ruth Burrows, and correspondence about it.
    - Travel files / Abe Burrows,., 1952-1953; 588290; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Correspondence, accounts, tickets, passport photos, pamphlets and maps for trips to England and France.
    - Travel files / Abe Burrows,., 1955 July-Sept; 588291; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Correspondence is mostly with Abe Burrows' secretary, Evelyn Greene, concerning his affairs while he was in California working as a screenwriter for Columbia Pictures Corporation.
    - Personal ephemera / Abe Burrows, 1960 and n.d; 588292; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Address lists for various parties including invitation, correspondence and guest list for Abe Burrows' 50th birthday party.
    - Personal ephemera / Abe Burrows,., 1953-1960; 588293; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Christmas gift and card lists.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows, 1950-1981 and n.d; 588294; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Holiday cards received.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1945-1955; 588295; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Thank you cards and letters received for professional appearances in fundraising drives and benefits and charitable contributions.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows, 1956-1970 and n.d; 588296; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows,., 1954-1957; 588297; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Correspondence on wardrobe.
    - Correspondence / Abe Burrows, 1946-1980 and n.d; 588298; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Unidentified correspondence, personal and professional letters, both incoming and outgoing, lacking last names.
    - Miscellaneous writings / Abe Burrows, n.d.; 588299; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Handwritten log [March-April, no year] of Burrow's arrival and early days at Silver Hill Inn, a medical treatment center.
    - Awards: Distinguished Achievement Award from Radio Life,., 1947-1948; 588300; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes Dinah Shore's award signed over to Burrows.
    - Awards: Screenwriters' Annual Award for Writing Achievement,., 1956, 1960 & 1967; 588301; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pulitzer Prize in Drama,., 1962 May 7; 588302; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Awarded to Burrows and Frank Loesser for How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying.